<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>anubitux.org</title>
    <link href="https://anubitux.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://anubitux.org" />
    <updated>2023-01-09T14:40:58+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Anu₿itux</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://anubitux.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>From wax tablets to elliptical curves. A Brief History of Cryptography (Part Two)</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/from-wax-tablets-to-elliptical-curves-a-brief-history-of-cryptography-part-two/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/from-wax-tablets-to-elliptical-curves-a-brief-history-of-cryptography-part-two/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/front.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="opsec"/>
            <category term="encryption"/>
            <category term="cryptography"/>
            <category term="crypto"/>
            <category term="anubitux"/>

        <updated>2023-01-09T14:40:58+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/front.jpg" alt="" />
                    After having broadly reviewed what we could call the genesis of cryptography, in this second article we will take us far forward in time, up to the present day. With the advent of modern electronic computers, it has been possible to exploit the computational power&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/front.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>After having broadly reviewed what we could call the <a href="https://anubitux.org/from-wax-tablets-to-elliptical-curves-a-brief-history-of-cryptography-part-one/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">genesis of cryptography</a>, in this second article we will take us far forward in time, up to the present day.</p>
<p>With the advent of modern electronic computers, it has been possible to exploit the computational power of processors in order to automate the procedures for coding and decoding messages.</p>
<p>Conceptually, even though centuries have passed, we still think in terms of algorithm, which represents the cryptographic method, and key, a string chosen by the user useful for encrypting and decrypting the message.</p>
<p>A substantial difference with respect to the past is given by the fact that electronic computers use only binary numbers as inputs, i.e., the numbers 0 and 1, with the combination of which all the other numbers, letters and symbols are composed. In particular, for the formation of the alphabet a conversion method called ASCII is used which allows to represent up to 128 alphabetic and symbolic characters through the combination of 7 binary digits.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the introduction of block encryption algorithms has made it possible to speed up the encryption/decryption processes by allowing the algorithm to be applied no longer to single elements, but to entire blocks of elements (composed of N bits), on which it is It is possible to carry out different types of operations, called iterations or rounds which, performed in sequence on each block processed, will lead to a greater or lesser complexity of the encryption algorithm.</p>
<p>Since the 1970s, together with the diffusion of personal computers, there has been great attention to the development of new encryption methods, which guarantee the best compromise between the level of security achieved and the complexity in computational terms of the algorithm adopted. The first of these was created by the German Horst Feistel (German naturalized US cryptographer who worked at IBM on the development of several famous ciphers) who, with his Lucifer cipher , laid the foundations for the Data Encryption Standard (called DES ) first protocol cipher officially adopted by the National Bureau of Standards of the United States ( National Institute of Standards and Technology, an agency of the government of the United States of America that deals with the management of technologies, today NIST ) in order to encrypt documents containing sensitive information ( a brief explanation of DES is available in <a href="https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/FIPS/NIST.FIPS.197.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this NIST document</a>).</p>
<p>After a few years, despite the improvements made over time, the DES protocol was supplanted by the more performing and secure Advanced Encryption Standard (= AES ) which, with its 128-bit blocks, could use 128, 192 or 256-bit keys and which , therefore, has been adopted by NIST to encrypt documents classified even as Top Secret (on <a href="https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/FIPS/NIST.FIPS.197.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this NIST page</a> an excellent presentation of the AES algorithm).</p>
<h3>Symmetric encryption and public key encryption</h3>
<p>After these very brief references, which I hope to have allowed us to understand how and why we have passed from an analogical to a digital encryption method, it would be appropriate to focus our attention on the functioning of some of them.</p>
<p>Among the encryption methods currently most used in the IT environment, a substantial distinction could be made based on the type of key used: symmetric key encryption and public key encryption.</p>
<p>In the first case, the key to encrypt and the one to decrypt will coincide, in the second case, however, it will be necessary to use two different keys (even if "linked" to each other).</p>
<p>One of the major problems of the first encryption methods, such as DES or AES, just mentioned, consisted in the need to create a rather long key, so as to be reasonably sure that the computational capabilities of the computers could not perform a so-called brute attack force, which is a method that consists of trying all possible combinations of keys. If it is true that it is possible to minimize this risk by simply increasing the length of the encryption key, so as to exponentially increase the calculation times and make a brute-force attack very difficult (if not impossible even with current hardware devices), one must however consider that the main flaw of the symmetric key method was the extreme difficulty in communicating the key to the recipient in a secure way.</p>
<p>This delicate step has been the Achilles' heel of encryption methods of this type for decades, prompting some scholars to look for one that would allow the sender and recipient of the message to communicate in total security.</p>
<p>In fact, there was a piece of history still to be written in cryptography. The moment this dilemma was resolved, a profound revolution would have taken place, in cryptography in particular, but also more generally in the methods of communication believed to be secure until then.</p>
<p>This epochal discovery took place in the 70s in America, developing the intuition had by the mathematicians Hellman, Diffie and Merkle according to which it was possible to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diffie%E2%80%93Hellman_key_exchange" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">exchange unencrypted values ​​useful for generating one's own encryption keys</a>, thanks to the use of functions called unidirectional , i.e. via non-reversible functions.</p>
<p>Shortly afterwards, thanks to the application of other scholars and cryptography enthusiasts such as Rivest, Shamir and Adleman , the cryptography system considered since then among the most important and innovative of this branch of science was developed: the RSA system (<a href="https://people.csail.mit.edu/rivest/Rsapaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here the paper</a>), also known as the public key cryptography system.</p>
<p>The innovative idea consisted in the presence of two different keys, one public, used to encrypt the message, the other private, used to decrypt it. This was made possible thanks to the use of a special one-way function, i.e., a function that was normally very difficult to reverse except under certain conditions (=the use of the private key).</p>
<p>In practice, to use this encryption, each user should have two keys, first of all creating a private key, to be jealously guarded, then deriving a public key from it. This key, as explained by the name itself, is not secret, on the contrary, for the purpose of correct encryption it is necessary to communicate it to the sender of the message, who will use it to encrypt his message thus sending it to the recipient without the worry of having to communicate the key, with the risks that would derive from it. Once the message has been delivered, for example via email, the recipient just has to decrypt the message using his own private key, the only one capable of inverting the special one-way function that underlies this method.</p>
<p>The classic example reported in scientific literature wants Alice and Bob to be willing to exchange a text message. Alice asks Bob for her public key, and Bob sends it to her. Using Bob's public key, Alice can encrypt the message and can proceed to send it. Once Bob has received the message, he can decrypt it using his private key.</p>
<p>In reality, the function used to implement this method is defined as unidirectional, but this does not mean that it is completely irreversible since, through factoring, it is possible to try to go back to the prime numbers used for the implementation of this cryptographic system, even if it is extremely expensive in terms of computational power. To overcome this type of problem, the use of keys that are at least 2048 bits long is now recommended.</p>
<p>On <a href="https://www.usna.edu/Users/cs/wcbrown/courses/si110AY13S/lec/l26/lec.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this page</a> you will find an explanation of this algorithm, even with some small illustrations that can facilitate understanding 😊. </p>
<p>For fans of numbers and mathematical problems, I recommend reading the book <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Xfermat-S-Last-Theorem-Pb/dp/0007902492" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fermat's Last Theorem</a>. The adventure of a genius, of a mathematical problem and of the man who solved it (I inserted the link on Amazon for simplicity's sake, but you can find it everywhere, even in any traditional bookstore) once again by Simon Singh, who managed to make a topic in itself difficult exciting, and moreover he succeeded in the huge aim of making me read an enormous amount of figures without me being bored!</p>
<h3>Hash functions</h3>
<p>Taking up the concept of non-invertible function described above, it will be easier at this point to introduce the concept of hash, since it is based on a one-way function, simple to compute but (hopefully) impossible to invert.</p>
<p>The purpose of this algorithm is to reduce a text (or input) of arbitrary length into a string (called hash value or message digest) of a fixed length.</p>
<p>Moreover, in addition to non-reversibility, therefore the impossibility of going back to the initial message starting from the hash value, this function must respect other important characteristics:</p>
<p>    • must produce a string that always has the same length regardless of the size of the input;<br>    • it must allow that, if the hashing function is repeated on the same message, the same output value is always calculated;<br>    • finally, it must ensure that at the slightest change in the input, the algorithm returns a completely different hash value.</p>
<p>The most used hashing protocols are: the MD5 algorithm , one of the first algorithms used for this purpose, very fast and still used to check the integrity of files; the family of SHA algorithms offers an increasing safety factor, the best known are SHA-1 and SHA-256 ; the series of RIPEMD algorithms , the best known of which is the RIPEMD-160, born as a European response to the American MD5 algorithm.</p>
<p>At <a href="https://md5calc.com/hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this address</a> we can have fun calculating the hash value for any portion of text and for files up to 10 MB, using numerous hashing algorithms.</p>
<p>The applications of such a function are many and more widespread than one might imagine. A first example of the use of hashing functions are password databases, where passwords are saved in the form of hash values ​​in order to prevent malicious people who come into possession of them from going back to the real passwords. </p>
<p>Another example would be file integrity checking, where you use the hash value as a checksum to make sure a particular file has not changed.</p>
<p>It is possible to verify the integrity of a message, by comparing the hash value calculated before and after the transmission of the message and verifying that no one has altered the source code since, due to the properties of this function, a minimal variation of the input would cause a complete hash value change. A useful application of this feature is the comparison with pre-compiled hash lists, in order to be able to quickly search for files already registered as viruses or containing malware in general.</p>
<p>Also, in computer forensics the hash function is widely used, in order to preserve the data that is acquired from any type of alteration or manipulation, allowing a rapid integrity check at any time. All data that is duplicated for forensic activities, in fact, assumes validity only if their congruence with the original data is verified.</p>
<p>For those who have never heard of computer forensics, I quote a very comprehensive definition:</p>
<p>“Forensic computer science is the discipline that studies the research, identification, collection, preservation, acquisition, analysis, presentation and evaluation of computer data for evidentiary purposes, in the context of criminal or civil procedural law. The science of computer forensics unfolds in different sectors of technology in order to allow the computer expert to acquire and analyse different types of devices and data.”.</p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.dalchecco.it/formazione/terminologia/informatica-forense/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.dalchecco.it/formazione/terminologia/informatica-forense/ </a></p>
<p>Any digital element can be used as an input value for a hash function. A string of text, an image, an audio file, an entire hard disk or any other digital data can "pass" through a specific hash function, returning a digest that will always have the same length, based on the algorithm used.</p>
<p>A few brief examples will undoubtedly offer an overview of the above concept, making the characteristics and utility of hash functions immediately identifiable. In particular, for such examples, the SHA-1 algorithm was used:</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/hash1-2.png" alt="" width="721" height="123" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash1-2-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash1-2-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash1-2-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash1-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash1-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash1-2-2xl.png 1600w">
<figcaption >Fig. 1: Example n. Hash function 1: This is an example message.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/hash2.png" alt="" width="721" height="122" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash2-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash2-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash2-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash2-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash2-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash2-2xl.png 1600w">
<figcaption >Fig. 2: Example no. hash function 2: This is an example message!</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Note how, as a single character in the input value varies between the two examples above (replacing the final punctuation mark of the example in Fig. 1 with an exclamation mark of the input value in Fig. 2), the result obtained was completely different.</p>
<p>In the same way, it will be easy to observe that, using a much longer text as input, the hash function always returns a value of the same length (the SHA-1 algorithm, taken for example, generates a message digest with a length of 160 bits, represented with 40 characters in hexadecimal value):</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/hash3.png" alt="" width="753" height="243" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash3-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash3-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash3-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash3-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash3-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/hash3-2xl.png 1600w">
<figcaption >Fig. 3: Example no. 3 of hash function: “Computers are incredibly fast, accurate and stupid; humans are incredibly slow, inaccurate and brilliant; together they are powerful beyond imagination."</figcaption>
</figure>
<h3>Digital signature</h3>
<p>A further application of public key cryptography, coupled with the characteristics of the hash algorithm, was the introduction of the so-called digital signature.</p>
<p>We have already seen that, given a document with content of arbitrary length, it is possible to reduce it to a string using the hash function. This string can be encrypted with the sender's private key, reversing the usual order. At this point, the document is ready to be sent unencrypted to the recipient, together with the digital signature and the sender's public key. The receiver, in turn, using the public key received from the sender, will be able to be certain that the message is authentic and also, by calculating the hash value, that no one has been able to make changes to the original message.</p>
<p>The following diagram will be useful in order to better understand what steps are necessary to apply the Digital Signature to a document:</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/firma-digitale.png" alt="" width="680" height="674" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/firma-digitale-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/firma-digitale-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/firma-digitale-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/firma-digitale-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/firma-digitale-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/57/responsive/firma-digitale-2xl.png 1600w">
<figcaption >Fig. 4: Operation diagram of the Digital Signature</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>In recent years, the digital signature has been widely used as well as further implemented, including through the use of smart cards, so as to assume a central role in digital communications, especially in the Public Administration. With D.Lgs. 82/2005, followed by D.Lgs. 235/2010, the Code for Digital Administration was introduced into Italian legislation, a body of rules with which the utmost importance was given to digital communications in the Public Administration, elevating the digital signature to a signature completely similar to the handwritten one (as indicated in article 21, paragraph 2, of Decreto Legislativo 7 marzo 2005, n. 82, published in the “Gazzetta Ufficiale” n. 112 of 16/05/2005).<br>Also in the Bitcoin protocol the developers have used the digital signature, together with the hash function, to digitally sign the transactions and verify that they originate from the real sender, but we will talk about this in the third and final part.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>FAQ</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/faq/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/faq/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/56/AnubituxWallpaperLightBlue.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-01-07T16:21:18+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/56/AnubituxWallpaperLightBlue.png" alt="" />
                    Here there are some answers to questions that users may have. If you have any doubt or need some support check also out our tutorials and do not hesitate to contact us. Anu₿itux is a customized Linux distribution based on Debian. It is designed to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/56/AnubituxWallpaperLightBlue.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p class="msg msg--highlight ">Here there are some answers to questions that users may have. If you have any doubt or need some support check also out our <a href="https://anubitux.org/tutorials-and-howtos/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tutorials</a> and do not hesitate to <a href="https://anubitux.org/meet-the-anubitux-project/">contact us</a>.</p>
<h5>What is Anu₿itux for?</h5>
<p>Anu₿itux is a customized Linux distribution based on Debian. It is designed to work as a live environment and aims to provide a safe and simple solution to use and manage cryptocurrency wallets, even for non-experienced users.</p>
<h5>What is the default user password?</h5>
<p>Anu₿itux has a default user that is <strong>anubitux</strong> and its password is <strong>anubitux</strong>. The user anubitux was added to the sudoers so it is possible to run commands that need root privileges.</p>
<h5>How to set up root password in Anu₿itux?</h5>
<p>Some actions, like autentication on some Wi-Fi network could need a root password to be performed. The user anubitux is in the sudoers but its password will not be accepted as a root password. To solve this simply run</p>
<p><code>sudo passwd</code></p>
<p>in your terminal and chose a password. If you are using Anu₿itux in live mode, this password will not be stored anywhere and has to be set-up again at every reboot.</p>
<h5>How to use Anu₿itux?</h5>
<p>Anu₿itux has beed designed to work as a live environment or, only for training purposes, as an installable Linux distribution that can be used as a virtual machine or on a dedicated device. To run it, please refer to <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-use-anubitux-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this post</a>.</p>
<h5>How to verify Anu₿itux?</h5>
<p>Every time a new release of Anu₿itux is released, checksums are updated on the <a href="https://anubitux.org/download-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">download page</a>. They are signen with our PGP key that we share on our <a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/Anubitux-PGP" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a>, on <a href="https://pastebin.com/bqmy9y2P" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PasteBin</a> and on <a href="https://keybase.io/anubitux" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">KeyBase</a>. To verify the signed checksums, please refer to <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-verify-your-downloaded-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this post</a>.</p>
<h5>How to verify Anu₿itux's tools?</h5>
<p>Anu₿itux's tools have been downloaded from the official debian reposotpries, from GitHub or as .appimage from the officla websites. GitHub tools and .appimages are placed in the /home/anubitux/Tools/ directory. Users can verify the source of the tools like Python scripts and verify checksums of the appimages comparing them to the official webisites of the tools. Doing so, users do not need to trust Anu₿itux but can easily verify by themselves that the Tools are genuine. All the links to sources and official websites can be found <a href="https://anubitux.org/what-is-anubitux-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</p>
<h5>How to update Anu₿itux?</h5>
<p>Anu₿itux works primarly as a live envirnment. Running commands like sudo apt update or sudo apt upgrade will have effect only on the current session and will not affect appimages and open source tools. The only way to update Anu₿itux is to <a href="https://anubitux.org/download-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">download</a> the last version checking the <a href="https://anubitux.org/changelog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">changelog</a>. We are releasing frequently a new version of Anu₿itux containing updates, some fixes and including users' <a href="https://anubitux.org/meet-the-anubitux-project/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">suggestions</a>.</p>
<h5>What should I do if I do not know how Anu₿itux's tools word?</h5>
<p>One of the main rules in the crypto world is "do not trust, verify!". Anu₿itux uses open source tools that can be verified by yourself or by someone you trust and appimages, so that you can verify the checksum of the tools by yourself referencing to the official sites. Link to sources and official websites can be found on <a href="https://anubitux.org/what-is-anubitux-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this page</a>. If you are in doubt about any tool or feature do not hesitate to <a href="https://anubitux.org/meet-the-anubitux-project/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">contact us</a>.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Happy Anew₿year! Anu₿itux 2 is out!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/happy-anewyear-anuitux-2-is-out/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/happy-anewyear-anuitux-2-is-out/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/load-2.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="team"/>
            <category term="python"/>
            <category term="project"/>
            <category term="opsec"/>
            <category term="live"/>
            <category term="linux for xmr"/>
            <category term="linux for cryptocurrencies"/>
            <category term="linux for crypto"/>
            <category term="linux for bitcoin"/>
            <category term="linux"/>
            <category term="links"/>
            <category term="install"/>
            <category term="downloads"/>
            <category term="download"/>
            <category term="distro"/>
            <category term="debian"/>
            <category term="cryptocurrency"/>
            <category term="crypto"/>
            <category term="changelog"/>
            <category term="bitcoin"/>
            <category term="anubitux"/>

        <updated>2023-01-01T12:33:01+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/load-2.png" alt="" />
                    Great news! Anu₿itux 2 is out! It is now based on Debian 11 bullseye and has a completely new user interface based on Cinnamon! Now user can chose at the boot if they want to run Anu₿itux in live mode, the main purpose of this&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/load-2.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Great news! <a href="https://anubitux.org/what-is-anubitux-2/">Anu₿itux 2</a> is out! It is now based on Debian 11 bullseye and has a completely new user interface based on Cinnamon!</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/Selection_127-2.png" alt="" width="800" height="391" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_127-2-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_127-2-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_127-2-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_127-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_127-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_127-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now user can chose at the boot if they want to run Anu₿itux in live mode, the main purpose of this project, or install it to train using its tools.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/Selection_116.png" alt="" width="600" height="451" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_116-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_116-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_116-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_116-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_116-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/54/responsive/Selection_116-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>It also has a lot of new tools and updates! <a href="https://anubitux.org/download-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Download</a> it and <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-use-anubitux-2/">check it out</a>!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Enable network monitor in Anu₿itux 2</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/enable-network-monitor-in-anubitux-2/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/enable-network-monitor-in-anubitux-2/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/cyberspace-gc66fcea74_1280.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="tutorial"/>
            <category term="opsec"/>
            <category term="network"/>
            <category term="linux for cryptocurrencies"/>
            <category term="linux for crypto"/>
            <category term="linux for bitcoin"/>
            <category term="anubitux"/>

        <updated>2023-01-01T00:02:00+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/cyberspace-gc66fcea74_1280.jpg" alt="Network" />
                    Anu₿itux is a linux distro based on Debian. By default, Anu₿itux has the network monitor enabled in the lower panel, but, it could not show any data because it needs to be configured accordingly to the network interfaces of the device you are using. To&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/cyberspace-gc66fcea74_1280.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Network" /></p>
                <p>Anu₿itux is a linux distro based on Debian. By default, Anu₿itux has the network monitor enabled in the lower panel, but, it could not show any data because it needs to be configured accordingly to the network interfaces of the device you are using.</p>
<p>To make it work properly, right click on the right part of the lower panel, near the notification area, as shown below.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/Selection_128.png" alt="" width="470" height="289" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_128-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_128-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_128-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_128-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_128-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_128-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Then click on Network interfaces and select the interfaces you want to be monitored, to show the inbound and outbound network traffic on your panel and always be able to see if something is going on.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/Selection_129.png" alt="" width="470" height="321" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_129-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_129-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_129-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_129-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_129-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_129-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now you will be able to see two coloured waves on the panel that symbolize the network load.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/Selection_130.png" alt="" width="298" height="90" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_130-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_130-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_130-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_130-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_130-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/53/responsive/Selection_130-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>This feature is very userful to notice if a service or a tool is doing some unexpected network traffic.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How to use Anu₿itux 2</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-use-anubitux-2/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/how-to-use-anubitux-2/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/space-shuttle-774_1280.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="vmware"/>
            <category term="virtualbox"/>
            <category term="virtual machine"/>
            <category term="ubuntu"/>
            <category term="tutorial"/>
            <category term="test"/>
            <category term="linux for cryptocurrencies"/>
            <category term="linux for crypto"/>
            <category term="linux for bitcoin"/>
            <category term="linux"/>
            <category term="kubuntu"/>
            <category term="balena"/>
            <category term="anubitux"/>
            <category term="USB"/>

        <updated>2023-01-01T00:01:00+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/space-shuttle-774_1280.jpg" alt="Start" />
                    On the web there is a lot of tutorials about how to use iso files containing Linux distributions or about how to import a virtual appliance in softwares like VirtualBox, so, here's another one. Of course, users may use any preferred and known solutions. These&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/space-shuttle-774_1280.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Start" /></p>
                <p>On the web there is a lot of tutorials about how to use iso files containing Linux distributions or about how to import a virtual appliance in softwares like <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VirtualBox</a>, so, here's another one. Of course, users may use any preferred and known solutions. These are only suggestions diirected to those who are not used to this type of files.</p>
<p>After you have <a href="https://anubitux.org/download-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">downloaded</a> the preferred version of Anu₿itux, please refer to the corresponding section of this page to start using it.</p>
<h3>Anu₿itux Live</h3>
<p>This is the main version of the Anu₿itux distro, designed to provide a safe environment and leave no traces on the devices used to run it. To use it, you'll need a USB stick and a software to flash the .iso file on it and make it bootable. For this purpose, we suggest <a href="https://www.balena.io/etcher/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Balena Etcher</a> which works on any kind of operative system, but there are many different solutions like <a href="https://rufus.ie/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rufus</a> for Windows or <a href="https://unetbootin.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">UNetbootin</a> for different OSes.</p>
<p>When using Balena Etcher, there is a very easy wizard to follow.</p>
<p>First of all plug in your USB stick and then click on the Flash from file" and select the .iso file you want to have on your USB stick.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-23-51.png" alt="Etcher1" width="819" height="526" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-23-51-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-23-51-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-23-51-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-23-51-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-23-51-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-23-51-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Then click on the "Select target" button and choose your USB stick. Do not forget that this process will overwrite all the content of the used drive, so, if needed, backup your files before completing this process.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-27-54.png" alt="Etcher2" width="819" height="526" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-27-54-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-27-54-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-27-54-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-27-54-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-27-54-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-27-54-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now click on the "Flash!" button (if using Linux provide your root password) and wait until the process ends.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-32-23.png" alt="etcher3" width="819" height="526" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-32-23-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-32-23-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-32-23-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-32-23-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-32-23-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-32-23-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>When finished, you can plug in the USB stick to the device you want to use with Anu₿itux and turn it on.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-38-04.png" alt="etcher4" width="819" height="526" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-38-04-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-38-04-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-38-04-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-38-04-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-38-04-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Screenshot-at-2022-06-30-12-38-04-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now you may need to enter your BIOS configuration and change the boot priority so that the USB device will be in the first position. Unless so, your device may boot your common operating system. In some cases, to change boot priority you may need to disable the secure boot features or change the boot mode settings. This procedure may be different depending on the used device. <a href="https://www.acronis.com/en-us/blog/posts/usb-boot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Here</a> you can find some useful suggestions about how to do that.</p>
<p>When your device boots from the USB drive containing Anu₿itux, we have to chose the Live (amd64) option tu run it in in Live mode and leave no traces on our device about what we are doing, unless we want.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_116.png" alt="" width="600" height="451" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_116-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_116-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_116-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_116-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_116-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_116-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h3>Anu₿itux install</h3>
<p>We could need to install Anu₿itux, maybe to run some tests on the tools or do some training with them. To install it on a dedicated device, we can arrange an USB drive following the steps shown above and, when booting from it, we have to chose the Start installer option.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_117.png" alt="" width="640" height="477" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now we have to follow the debian installation wizard.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight ">It is suggested to chose anubitux as username, to be sure that all the tools run properly.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selezione_108.png" alt="" width="800" height="594" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selezione_108-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selezione_108-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selezione_108-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selezione_108-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selezione_108-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selezione_108-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>When arriving at the step where we have to chose the root password, we can leave it blank, so that our user will automatically be allowed to run administrative commands with sudo, and have a more "<em>ubuntu-like</em>" user experience.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_109.png" alt="" width="790" height="512" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_109-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_109-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_109-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_109-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_109-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_109-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>We may also install it in a virtual machine like <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VirtualBox</a> or <a href="https://www.vmware.com/products/workstation-player.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VMWare Player</a>.</p>
<h5>VIrtualBox</h5>
<p>First of all create a new virtual machine (Machine -&gt; New) and fill the form as preferred or like suggested in the following picture, providing the iso file of Anu₿itux.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_118-2.png" alt="" width="800" height="483" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_118-2-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_118-2-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_118-2-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_118-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_118-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_118-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>It is very important to check the "Skip Unattended Installation" option, to avoid running issues due to some wrong configuration that VirtualBox could automatically make.</p>
<p>In the next step we have to assing the resources to our virtual machine. This depends on the host machine we are using to run the VM.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_119.png" alt="" width="800" height="484" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_119-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_119-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_119-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_119-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_119-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_119-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Then we have to chose the size of the virtual drive: 20 GB should be enough.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_120.png" alt="" width="800" height="475" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_120-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_120-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_120-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_120-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_120-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_120-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now we are ready to run our virtual machine and install it following the steps of the debian installer wizard.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_117-2.png" alt="" width="640" height="477" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-2-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-2-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-2-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>For a better user experience, it is suggested to install the <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/manual/ch01.html#intro-installing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VirtualBox Extension Pack</a> on your host system and the <a href="https://linuxconfig.org/install-virtualbox-guest-additions-on-linux-guest" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VirtualBox Guest Additions</a> in your virtual machine.</p>
<h5>VMWare Player</h5>
<p>To install and run Anu₿itux in a VMWare virtual machine, open <a href="https://www.vmware.com/it/products/workstation-player.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VMWare Player</a> and click on "Create a New Virtual Machine".</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/vmw1.png" alt="vmw1" width="791" height="543" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/vmw1-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/vmw1-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/vmw1-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/vmw1-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/vmw1-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/vmw1-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In the next window select the "Use ISO image:" option, click on "Browse..." and select the Anu₿itux iso image you wish to install.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_121.png" alt="" width="770" height="680" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_121-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_121-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_121-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_121-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_121-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_121-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In the next window select the "Linux" option and choose "Debian 11.x 64-bit" from the list.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_122.png" alt="" width="770" height="676" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_122-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_122-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_122-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_122-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_122-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_122-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In the next window choose a name for your virtual machine and the folder where VMWare player is going to store the files.</p>
<p>Then choose the maximum size of the virtual har disk that the virtual machine will use. Make sure to select the "Split disk into multiple files option" to avoid an excessive disk space consumption. A size of 20 GB should be appropriate for running some tests on Anu₿itux and its tools.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_123.png" alt="" width="770" height="679" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_123-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_123-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_123-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_123-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_123-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_123-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In the next window you can click "Customize Hardware..." to change settings like the number of processors to assign to the virtual machine. Then you can click "Finish" and run your virtual machine.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_124.png" alt="" width="770" height="622" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_124-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_124-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_124-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_124-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_124-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_124-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now you can start the virtual machine and select the "Start Installer" option.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/Selection_117-3.png" alt="" width="640" height="477" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-3-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-3-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-3-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-3-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-3-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/Selection_117-3-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>After doing that you only have to follow the Debian installer wizard.</p>
<p>Debian usually has the open-vm-tools installed by default, but for a better user experience you could also install the "<a href="https://kb.vmware.com/s/article/1035392" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VMware Tools</a>".</p>
<h3>Anu₿itux virtual machine</h3>
<p>On the <a href="https://anubitux.org/download-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">download page</a> there is also a ready to use Anu₿itux virtual machine. To use it, first of all, you need to have <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIrtualBox</a> installed. You may also install the <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/manual/ch01.html#intro-installing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VirtualBox Extension Pack</a> to increase the features of your virtual machine.</p>
<p>Then you simply have to click on "File" -&gt; "Import Appliance..." and select the .ova file you have downloaded.</p>
<p>Then select the "Local File System" option and choose the .ova file to import.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/ova1.png" alt="ova1" width="1085" height="826" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova1-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova1-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova1-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova1-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova1-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova1-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Then simply click on "Next &gt;" and on "Import".</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/ova2.png" alt="ova2" width="1085" height="826" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova2-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova2-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova2-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova2-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova2-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/52/responsive/ova2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Then, when the import process is complete, the virtual machine will appera in the left side of the VirtualBox client, where al the virtual appliances are listed. Now you can start Anu₿itux or click on the "Settings" button to customize the hardware assigned to it.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What is Anu₿itux?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/what-is-anubitux-2/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/what-is-anubitux-2/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Screenshot_20221226_120241.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="wallet"/>
            <category term="ubuntu"/>
            <category term="tutorial"/>
            <category term="tools"/>
            <category term="tool"/>
            <category term="script"/>
            <category term="python"/>
            <category term="live"/>
            <category term="linux for cryptocurrencies"/>
            <category term="linux for crypto"/>
            <category term="linux for bitcoin"/>
            <category term="linux"/>
            <category term="distro"/>
            <category term="cryptocurrency"/>
            <category term="crypto"/>
            <category term="bitcoin"/>
            <category term="anubitux"/>

        <updated>2023-01-04T12:44:37+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Screenshot_20221226_120241.png" alt="AnuBituxDesktop" />
                    Anu₿itux is, first of all, a Debian based distro that aims to provide a simple and safe environment to use and manage cryptocurrencies. Its aim is to allow all the users to safeguard their cryptos and their privacy like pros, without the need to prepare&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Screenshot_20221226_120241.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="AnuBituxDesktop" /></p>
                <p>Anu₿itux is, first of all, a <a href="https://debian.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Debian</a> based distro that aims to provide a <strong>simple</strong> and <strong>safe</strong> environment to use and manage cryptocurrencies. Its aim is to allow all the users to safeguard their cryptos and their privacy like pros, without the need to prepare any complex set-up. But it is not only a customized operative system, it also wants to be a place to share knowledge and best practices, providing tutorials based on Anu₿itux that can be applied in every situation.</p>
<h3>What is included in the Anu₿itux OS?</h3>
<p>As mentioned, Anu₿itux is an environment based on Debian 11 Bullseye but with many customizations:</p>
<ul>
<li>it includes a lot of useful tools to manage cryptocurrencies, like address generators and desktop wallets. Many tools are includes as AppImages, so that end-users will be able to check hashes by themselves;</li>
<li>the Firefox browser is improved to prevent fingerprinting and the storage of any kind of information on the device. It also has a lot of useful and interesting bookmarks to easily reach online resources;</li>
<li>if more privacy is neede, <a href="https://www.torproject.org/download/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tor Browser</a> is also available;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Und3rf10w/kali-anonsurf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AnonSurf</a> has been added, to help users safeguard their privacy while accessing online resources;</li>
<li>Python tools run in dedicated <a href="https://anubitux.org/anubitux-and-python-virtual-environments/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">virtual environments</a>;</li>
<li>many printer drivers are installed. They could be useful to generate and print paper wallets completely offline;</li>
<li>it also includes many solutions to recover access to lost wallets;</li>
<li>and more...</li>
</ul>
<p>The most significant part of Anu₿itux is his collection of tools. Some of them have been selected for this environment, others have been <a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">developed</a> by the Anu₿itux team to fit the needs that users may encounter.</p>
<h3>Tools list</h3>
<p>The tools are placed in dedicated sub-menus, divided into different categories so that users will be able to quickly find what they need. Some tools did not provide a menu entry. In this case, Anu₿itux has arranged a custom menu entry that also shows some useful information about the tool, like examples and suggestions.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Selection_111.png" alt="" width="240" height="553" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_111-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_111-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_111-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_111-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_111-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_111-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h4>Address generators</h4>
<p>The first category is dedicated to the address generators, a collection of tools that could be used to securely generate crypto addresses to store, for instance, on a paper wallet.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Selection_113.png" alt="" width="370" height="219" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_113-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_113-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_113-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_113-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_113-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_113-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pointbiz/bitaddress.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BitAddress</a> is a javascript tool that runs locally and creates a Bitcoin paper wallet and that can be found at <a href="https://www.bitaddress.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">bitaddress.org</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dashpay/paper.dash.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DashPaperWallet</a> is a javascript tool that runs locally and creates a Dash paper wallet that can be found on <a href="https://paper.dash.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">paper.dash.org</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/Dice2Seed" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dice2Seed</a> is a tool that obtaines a mnemonic seed starting from the entropy obtained rolling a dice;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/DiceTracker.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DiceTracker</a> is a tool that generates printable paper wallets starting from 256 dice rolls, removing the need to trust software's entropy;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/moneromooo-monero/monero-wallet-generator/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MoneroWalletGenerator</a> is an offline Monero wallet generator that can also be found on <a href="https://moneroaddress.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">moneroaddress.org</a>; </li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/walletgeneratornet/WalletGenerator.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WalletGenerator</a> is a multi-currency paper wallet generator that supports dozens of different coins;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/luigi1111/xmr.llcoins.net/blob/master/site/addressgen.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">XMR AddressGen</a> is a tool to generate XMR addresses that can also be reached on <a href="https://xmr.llcoins.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this</a> website.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Encryption</h4>
<p>Here there are tools that could be useful to interact with anything regarding encryption.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Screenshot_20221226_191603.png" alt="" width="300" height="172" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191603-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191603-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191603-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191603-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191603-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191603-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://bitwarden.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BitWarden</a> is a very popular, powerful and <a href="https://github.com/bitwarden" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open source</a> password manager;</li>
<li><a href="https://keepassxc.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">KeepassXC</a> is an offline <a href="https://github.com/keepassxreboot/keepassxc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open source</a> cross-platform password manager, that could also store any kind of information like mnemonic seed phrases;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.openpgp.org/software/kleopatra/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kleopatra</a> manages PGP Keys and allows to encrypt, decrypt, sign and verify text and files;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.veracrypt.fr/en/Home.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VeraCrypt</a> is a cross-platform <a href="https://github.com/veracrypt/VeraCrypt" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open source</a> tool that allows to encrypt and decrypt volumes and disks with many algorithms;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mhogomchungu/zuluCrypt" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">zuluCrypt</a> is a simple,feature rich and powerful solution for hard drives encryption. More info <a href="https://mhogomchungu.github.io/zuluCrypt/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Hardware Wallets</h4>
<p>This category encloses the official clients of some hardware wallets. Many of them are also supported by desktop clients like Electrum, since the udev rules have been set up in Anu₿itux so that they can be connected without troubles. </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Selection_126.png" alt="" width="350" height="190" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_126-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_126-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_126-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_126-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_126-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_126-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://bc-vault.com/download/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BC Vault</a> is the official client to manage <a href="https://bc-vault.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BCVault hardware wallets</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/digitalbitbox/bitbox-wallet-app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BitBoxApp</a> is the official client to manage <a href="https://shiftcrypto.ch/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BitBox hardware wallets</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ledger.com/ledger-live" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ledger Live</a> is the official client to manage <a href="https://www.ledger.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ledger hardware wallets</a> like the Nano S model and the Nano X model;</li>
<li>Setup udev rules is a script that sets up the udev rules, needed by the clients to interact with hardware wallets (this is done completely offline);</li>
<li><a href="https://suite.trezor.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Trezor Suite</a> is the official client to manage <a href="https://trezor.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Trezor hardware wallets</a> like the Model One and the Model T.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Recovery</h4>
<p>In this section there is a collection of tool that could help to recover access to lost wallets or locked funds.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Screenshot_20221226_191238.png" alt="" width="300" height="276" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191238-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191238-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191238-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191238-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191238-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_191238-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/BTCKeySearch" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BTCKeySearch</a> is a tool , developed by the Anu₿itux team, that scans files in a directory and in its subdirectories, looking for Bitcoin private keys, Monero private spend keys and BIP32 root keys (xpriv);</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/simsong/bulk_extractor" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BulkExtractor</a> is a tool that rapidly scans directory and volumes for any kind of input like regular expressions;</li>
<li><a href="https://hashcat.net/hashcat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">HashCat</a> is a very popular password cracking tool that supports a lot of different algorithms. Please refer to the <a href="https://hashcat.net/forum/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">official forum</a> to learn how to use it in every specific case;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cgsecurity/testdisk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Photorec</a> tries to recover deleted files or part of them and could be useful, for instance, for accidentally deleted wallets.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/SeedSearch.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SeedSearch</a> is a tool, developed by the Anu₿itux team, that scans files in a directory and in its subdirectories, looking for BIP39 mnemonic seeds;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/gurnec/btcrecover/blob/master/docs/Seedrecover_Quick_Start_Guide.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SeedRecover</a> is part of the BTCrecover tool. It tries to fix a mnemonic seed phrase with mistakes and/or missing words;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/SeedSearch.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SeedSearch</a> is a tool, developed by the Anu₿itux team, that scans files in a directory and in its subdirectories, looking for BIP39 mnemonic seeds;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/VeraDecrypt.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VeraDecrypt</a> is a tool, developed by the Anu₿itux team, that tries to unlock <a href="https://www.veracrypt.fr/en/Home.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VeraCrypt</a> volumes and containers using a list of passwords given by the user.</li>
</ul>
<h4>UsefulTools</h4>
<p>In this section there are some tools that could be useful in many Anu₿itux's use cases.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Screenshot_20221226_192634.png" alt="" width="350" height="289" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_192634-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_192634-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_192634-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_192634-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_192634-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_192634-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://ffmpeg.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">FFMpeg</a> is a complete, cross-platform solution to record, convert and stream audio and video. For this purpose, it could be used to record the desktop screen while doing operations that need to be reported to a third party. <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #e03e2d; text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Never</strong></span></span> use it while generating sensible information like private keys or new wallets or, in general, for information that are not supposed to be shared;</li>
<li><a href="https://flameshot.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Flameshot</a> is a powerful tool to capture and edit screenshots</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/passgen.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Password (passgen.py)</a> is a secure password generator developed by the Anu₿itux team;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/fukuchi/libqrencode/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QREncode</a> is a tool that generates QR codes from strings and that could be very useful to store addresses and keys offline. More information <a href="https://fukuchi.org/works/qrencode/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sayanarijit/qrscan" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QRScan</a> is a lightweight QR scanner with a terminal user interface (TUX) that works on files and throught the webcam;</li>
<li><a href="https://debian.pkgs.org/11/debian-main-amd64/qtqr_2.0~bzr33-2_all.deb.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QtQR</a> is a GUI tool to generate and scan QR codes; </li>
<li><a href="https://tshark.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TShark</a> is a CLI tool for packet capturing;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.wireshark.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wireshark</a> is the world’s foremost and widely-used network protocol analyzer. It could be used to capture network traffic during sensible operations and verify that only proper network traffic was exchanged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Wallets</h4>
<p>In this category there is a collection of many desktop wallets, so that the users, in most cases, will be able to use their coins without the need to install any client.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Screenshot_20221226_193930.png" alt="" width="390" height="342" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_193930-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_193930-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_193930-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_193930-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_193930-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Screenshot_20221226_193930-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.coinomi.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Coinomi</a> is a multi-chain wallet that is widely used;</li>
<li><a href="https://electroncash.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ElectronCash</a> is a version of the well known Electrum wallet that works with Bitcoin Cash;</li>
<li><a href="https://electrum-ltc.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Electrum(LTC)</a> is a version of the well known Electrum wallet that works with Litecoin;</li>
<li><a href="https://electrum.org/#home" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Electrum(BTC)</a> is one of the most known and used SPV Bitcoin wallets; </li>
<li><a href="https://www.exodus.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Exodus</a> is a multi-currency and multi-service desktop wallet;</li>
<li><a href="https://featherwallet.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">FeatherWallet</a> is a very complete and powerful Monero wallet with a comfortable user interface that is similar to Electrum's one;</li>
<li><a href="https://blockstream.com/green/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GreenWallet</a> is a desktop wallet, <a href="https://github.com/Blockstream/green_qt/releases" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">developed</a> by <a href="https://blockstream.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blockstream</a> that supports Bitcoin and even L-BTC on the <a href="https://blockstream.com/liquid/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Liquid</a> sidechain.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.getmonero.org/resources/user-guides/monero-wallet-cli.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Monero-CLI</a> is the official command line Monero wallet;</li>
<li><a href="https://mycrypto.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MyCrypto</a> is a wallet that allows to manage Ethereum accounts;</li>
<li><a href="https://mymonero.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MyMonero</a> is a lightweight and efficient Monero wallet;</li>
<li><a href="https://sparrowwallet.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sparrow wallet</a> is a Bitcoin wallet caring for user's privacy;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.zecwallet.co/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ZecWallet Lite</a> is a fully featured shielded wallet for Zcash;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/MetaMask/metamask-extension/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MetaMask</a> is a wallet for Ethereum accounts and a gateway to blockchain apps. It can be found as an extension of the FireFox browser;</li>
<li><a href="https://templewallet.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Temple</a> is a Tezos wallet that can be found as an extension of the FireFox browser.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Wallet Tools</h4>
<p>In this section there are tools that can be used to manage wallet related stuff, especially mnemonic seed phrases.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/Selection_114.png" alt="" width="370" height="338" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_114-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_114-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_114-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_114-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_114-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/51/responsive/Selection_114-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/iancoleman/bip39" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BIP39</a> is the well known tool developed by Ian Coleman that handles derivation paths based on BIP39 wordlists. It is also available on his <a href="https://iancoleman.io/bip39/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">website</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/OutCast3k/coinbin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Coinb.in</a> is a tool that allows users to sign, verify and broadcast transactions that could also have been written from scratch. The tool is also available on the web at the <a href="https://coinb.in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">coinb.in</a> page.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/luigi1111/xmr.llcoins.net/blob/master/site/addresstests.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">XMR Address Test</a> is a tool related to Cryptonote Addresses, used by the Monero protocol;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/luigi1111/xmr.llcoins.net/blob/master/site/checktx.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">XMR check tx</a> is a tool that can be used to verify XMR transactions, providing the necessary keys;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/luigi1111/xmr.llcoins.net/blob/master/site/sign.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">XMR message sign</a> can be used to sign and verify messages using XMR keys;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/SeedCheck.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SeedCheck.py</a> is a tool developed by the Anu₿itux team that tries to find out the correct derivation path or the right software a seed was used with.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How to create a &quot;view-only&quot; wallet for our cold storage</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-create-a-view-only-wallet-for-our-cold-storage/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/how-to-create-a-view-only-wallet-for-our-cold-storage/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Golde_Eye.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="wallet"/>
            <category term="ubuntu"/>
            <category term="tutorial"/>
            <category term="tools"/>
            <category term="tool"/>
            <category term="private key"/>
            <category term="password"/>
            <category term="paper wallet"/>
            <category term="opsec"/>
            <category term="monero"/>
            <category term="linux for xmr"/>
            <category term="linux for cryptocurrencies"/>
            <category term="linux for crypto"/>
            <category term="linux for bitcoin"/>
            <category term="linux"/>
            <category term="howto"/>
            <category term="electrum"/>
            <category term="cryptocurrency"/>
            <category term="crypto"/>
            <category term="caution"/>
            <category term="bitcoin"/>
            <category term="bip39"/>
            <category term="anubitux"/>

        <updated>2022-12-21T23:46:53+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Golde_Eye.png" alt="" />
                    Let's hypothesize we arranged our super secure cold storage to "hodl" cryptos until they get to the moon, maybe using one of our tools like dicetracker or dice2seed! It could be very useful to be able to monitor our addresses, not only to see how&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Golde_Eye.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Let's hypothesize we arranged our super secure cold storage to "hodl" cryptos until they get to the moon, maybe using one of our tools like <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-generate-random-paper-wallets-with-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">dicetracker</a> or <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-generate-a-mnemonic-seed-with-anubitux-and-a-dice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">dice2seed</a>! It could be very useful to be able to monitor our addresses, not only to see how we are getting to the moon but also to be sure that our funds are safe and our cold storage is working properly. To do that, of course, we could take note of our public addresses and check them periodically on some block explorer. We can find a lot of them in Firefox's bookmarks in Anu₿itux. To perform this task in a better way, we could arrange a view-only wallet, a wallet that is only able to see what's going on with our addresses but does not know our private keys so that it will be unable to sign transactions and spend our funds.</p>
<p class="msg msg--warning"><strong>Never send or request funds to addresses that are in our view-only wallets if we are not sure to be able to access the corresponding private keys!</strong></p>
<h3>Bitcoin watching-only wallet</h3>
<p>With Bitcoin addresses, one of the best tools to arrange a watching-only wallet is <a href="https://electrum.org/#home" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Electrum</a>. We could arrange it using public addresses or master public keys, depending on how we created our cold storage.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">OPSEC TIP: wallets like the ones proposed in this post are called SPV wallets. They use other's nodes to check our balances. If available, we should set up our clients to connect only to trusted nodes (we will discuss it in further posts, keep following us).</p>
<h4>Public addresses</h4>
<p>In the first case, let's hypothesize we took note of our public addresses and would like to monitor them comfortably through Electrum. To do that let's start Electrum from the Wallets menu in Anu₿itux and create a new wallet, selecting the "Import Bitcoin addresses or private keys" option.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_086.png" alt="" width="600" height="425" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_086-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_086-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_086-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_086-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_086-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_086-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In the next step, we can type or paste our public addresses in the proper box.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_087.png" alt="" width="600" height="431" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_087-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_087-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_087-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_087-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_087-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_087-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now, clicking on next, we can provide a password and then we will have our watching-only wallet.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_088.png" alt="" width="600" height="404" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_088-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_088-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_088-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_088-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_088-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_088-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h4>Electrum Master Public Key</h4>
<p>If we created our seed using Electrum, maybe using the advanced feature to obtain a <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-generate-24-words-mnemonic-seeds-with-electrum/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">24 words mnemonic seed phrase</a>, we could obtain our master public key and use it to set up a new watching-only wallet. Using master keys allows us to create hierarchical deterministic (HD) watching-only wallets. With this kind of wallet, we are able to obtain all the same addresses that we could obtain in our main wallet, related to our mnemonic seed. It could also be very useful if we want to be able to receive transactions on many different public addresses, obtaining them without the need to access our cold storage and keep our private keys safe.</p>
<p>To obtain our master public key, we only have to go to the Wallet menu and click on Information.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_089.png" alt="" width="350" height="313" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_089-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_089-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_089-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_089-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_089-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_089-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In the next window we will see a lot of information about our wallet, like our Master Public Key.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_090.png" alt="" width="800" height="515" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_090-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_090-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_090-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_090-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_090-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_090-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Let's take note of it and let's create a new Standard wallet.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  msg--info">OPSEC TIP: It could be a good idea to access our wallet only in Anu₿itux live and offline, extract our Master Public Key and use it to create our watching-only wallet in a separate working environment that we will connect to the Internet.</p>
<p>In the second step of the creation wizard, we have to choose the "Use a Master Key" option.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_091.png" alt="" width="600" height="428" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_091-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_091-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_091-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_091-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_091-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_091-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now we only have to type or paste the Master Public Key and we have set up our watch-only wallet. </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_092.png" alt="" width="600" height="434" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_092-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_092-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_092-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_092-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_092-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_092-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>As we can see in the following screenshot, we obtained the same addresses in both wallets, with the difference that only one of them would be able to spend the funds we could receive.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_093.png" alt="" width="1000" height="379" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_093-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_093-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_093-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_093-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_093-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_093-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h4>Master Public Key</h4>
<p>Let's now hypothesize we want to create a watch-only wallet related to a BIP39 seed. To obtain the Master Public Key we could import our BIP39 seed creating a new Electrum wallet, taking care to specify the right derivation path, and obtain it with the same steps we have seen above, or we could use the <a href="https://github.com/iancoleman/bip39" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ian Coleman BIP39 tool</a>.</p>
<p>Typing the seed in the proper box and selecting the desired derivation path, we will obtain the addresses and the private keys that could be derived from that seed and also many master keys. We are interested in the one named "Account Extended Public Key".</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_094.png" alt="" width="1000" height="655" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_094-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_094-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_094-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_094-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_094-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_094-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Do not use the "BIP32 Extended Public Key" since it will show different addresses and sending transactions to them could give us some trouble accessing our funds (do not worry, it can be done with the "BIP32 Extended Private Key").</p>
<p>To confirm that the Master Public Key we have chosen is the right one, we can compare the obtained addresses.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_095.png" alt="" width="800" height="447" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_095-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_095-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_095-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_095-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_095-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_095-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h3>Monero view-only wallet</h3>
<p>As stated in <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-spend-a-monero-paper-wallet-with-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">other posts</a>, Monero works with two kinds of private keys, a private spend key to sign transactions and a private view key to view information about our addresses since with Monero we can't check information about public addresses as we are used to do with Bitcoin and other cryptos. The private view key is the one we are going to use to set up our watch-only wallets.</p>
<p>For the following examples we are going to use a Monero Paper Wallet generated with our tool <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-generate-random-paper-wallets-with-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">dicetracker</a>.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_106.png" alt="" width="550" height="628" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_106-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_106-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_106-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_106-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_106-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_106-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h4>Feather wallet</h4>
<p>To set up a watch-only wallet with <a href="https://featherwallet.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Feather Wallet</a>, we have to start the wallet creation wizard and select the "Restore wallet from keys" option.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_096.png" alt="" width="575" height="576" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_096-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_096-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_096-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_096-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_096-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_096-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In the next step we have to provide the Primary address and the Secret view Key. The tool itself gives us the tip to not insert the Secret spend key if we are creating a view-only wallet.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_097.png" alt="" width="575" height="581" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_097-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_097-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_097-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_097-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_097-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_097-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now we only have to provide the wallet creation date and a password and our watch-only wallet is ready. If we are not sure about the wallet creation date, we can provide a date we are sure is earlier than it, unless so the wallet could not scan some blocks including transactions that we could be interested in.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_098.png" alt="" width="1000" height="532" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_098-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_098-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_098-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_098-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_098-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_098-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h4>Monero CLI</h4>
<p>To create a view-only wallet using the <a href="https://www.getmonero.org/downloads/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Monero official</a> command line interface wallet, we have to start it with the <em>--generate-from-view-key</em> option followed by the name we are giving to our watch-only wallet. In Anu₿itux you can type:</p>
<p><code>Tools/AddressGen/monero-x86_64-linux-gnu-v0.18.1.2/monero-wallet-cli --generate-from-view-key wallet_name</code></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_099.png" alt="" width="900" height="204" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_099-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_099-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_099-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_099-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_099-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_099-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>With commands like <em>balance</em> and <em>wallet_info</em> we can obtain some information about our wallet.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_100.png" alt="" width="700" height="416" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_100-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_100-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_100-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_100-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_100-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_100-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>And with commands like <em>address all</em> and <em>address new</em> we will obtain addresses we could share to request transactions.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_101.png" alt="" width="800" height="76" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_101-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_101-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_101-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_101-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_101-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_101-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h3>Ethereum view-only wallet</h3>
<p>To obtain a view-only wallet with Ethereum we could use <a href="https://mycrypto.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MyCrypto</a>, which can be started from the Anu₿itux Wallets menu, and a public address we obtained previously with any desired method.</p>
<p>To obtain our view-only wallet, we only have to start MyCrypto, click on the "View &amp; Send" button on the left of the screen and then click on the </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_102.png" alt="" width="1000" height="528" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_102-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_102-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_102-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_102-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_102-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_102-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now we only have to type or paste our address and our view-only wallet is ready to be used.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_104.png" alt="" width="500" height="301" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_104-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_104-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_104-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_104-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_104-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_104-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In this way we can easily monitor our Ethereum account, even for token transactions, without exposing our private keys or our mnemonic seeds.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/Selection_105.png" alt="" width="900" height="704" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_105-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_105-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_105-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_105-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_105-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Selection_105-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h3>Final thoughts</h3>
<p>Using view-only wallets allows us to manage and monitor our addresses without exposing our private keys unless we need to dispose transactions. It is a very useful feature of many software wallets that we should consider if we are not doing transactions on a regular basis. We only have to remember that obtaining master public keys implies that we are handling our private keys or our seed and this operation has to be done very carefully, to avoid any risk concerning the safety of our funds.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Hide your mnemonic seed with steganography</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/hide-your-mnemonic-seed-with-steganography/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/hide-your-mnemonic-seed-with-steganography/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/steganography.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="wallet"/>
            <category term="ubuntu"/>
            <category term="tutorial"/>
            <category term="tools"/>
            <category term="tool"/>
            <category term="password"/>
            <category term="opsec"/>
            <category term="offline"/>
            <category term="live"/>
            <category term="linux for cryptocurrencies"/>
            <category term="linux for crypto"/>
            <category term="linux"/>
            <category term="kubuntu"/>
            <category term="howto"/>
            <category term="encrypted"/>
            <category term="distro"/>
            <category term="cryptocurrency"/>
            <category term="crypto"/>
            <category term="caution"/>
            <category term="bip39"/>
            <category term="anubitux"/>

        <updated>2022-12-07T21:13:57+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/steganography.png" alt="" />
                    The ideas presented in this post and in other similar posts on this website have to be considered only like suggestions. Users should adopt the strategies that better fit their threat model and their needs. Hiding a mnemonic seed is something about everyone has his&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/steganography.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p class="msg msg--warning">The ideas presented in this post and in other similar posts on this website have to be considered only like suggestions. Users should adopt the strategies that better fit their threat model and their needs.</p>
<p>Hiding a mnemonic seed is something about everyone has his theories but no one is able to provide the correct solution. We believe that there is no universal solution, but only a lot of different solutions that fit the needs of one user or another.</p>
<p>A good strategy could be to hide our mnemonic seed with steganography. For those who do not know what it is, steganography is the practice of representing a piece of information within another object in a way that could not be easily seen by others. So we could try to hide our mnemonic seed in another file, like a picture or a video. Let's see how we could do it with Anu₿itux.</p>
<h3>The procedure</h3>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong>To safeguard the security of this process, we kindly suggest following all these steps using Anu₿itux live without connecting it to the internet and disabling all the network interfaces with the proper desktop shortcut.</strong></p>
<p>First of all, we need a mnemonic seed to hide. We could obtain it with dice rolls using our tool <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-generate-a-mnemonic-seed-with-anubitux-and-a-dice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dice2Seed</a>, or we could obtain it with <a href="https://anubitux.org/how-to-generate-24-words-mnemonic-seeds-with-electrum/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Electrum</a> wallet, or with any other tool we think is the best for our needs.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_075.png" alt="mnemonic" width="900" height="526" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_075-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_075-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_075-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_075-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_075-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_075-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now we can store it in a text file, since we are assuming we are working in a live and offline environment, in most cases this should imply no risks. We can use this command to easily do that</p>
<p class="align-center"><code>echo 'your words here' &gt; Documents/mnemonic</code></p>
<p>Now we can choose a file to hide our mnemonic seed in. In this case, we are using a copy of the Anu₿itux wallpaper. </p>
<p class="msg msg--warning">It is recommended to do this procedure on a copy of your files, to avoid corrupting or losing them if something goes wrong during the process.</p>
<p>To hide our mnemonic, we are going to use ZuluCrypt. We can find its GUI in the Anu₿itux encryption menu. The required feature, "Encrypted Container Hidden In Video/Cover File (Steganography)" can be found in the "Create" menu. </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_076.png" alt="zuluc" width="800" height="461" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_076-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_076-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_076-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_076-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_076-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_076-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Clicking on it we have to provide the file we want to use to hide our information, a password to unlock it and the desired size.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_077.png" alt="zulus" width="650" height="377" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_077-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_077-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_077-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_077-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_077-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_077-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>In this case, a size of 1 MB will be enough: if we are going to associate a big container with our picture, it would have a very big size that could look suspicious and attract undesired attention.</p>
<p>We also absolutely need to take care of the "Volume Offset" value, because we will need it every time we are going to unlock the container. It is calculated by the tool and indicates where it should look for the container to unlock.</p>
<p>Now we only have to click the "Create" button and our secret container is ready to be mounted. Before doing that, let's take a look at the size of the file we used to hide the container in.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_078.png" alt="filesize" width="550" height="166" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_078-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_078-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_078-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_078-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_078-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_078-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>As we can see, the file we used for the procedure, even if it looks identical to the original one, has a bigger size of about 1.4 MB.</p>
<p>Now, let's access our container to store the mnemonic seed into it. We can do this with ZuluCrypt, using the "Volume Hosted In A File" feature under the "Open" menu. </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_079.png" alt="zuluopen" width="750" height="433" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_079-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_079-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_079-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_079-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_079-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_079-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Now we have to:</p>
<ul>
<li>provide the file we used to hide the container;</li>
<li>select "PLAIN dm-crypt" as "Volume Type";</li>
<li>type the Offset value provided by the tool during the creation of the container;</li>
<li>type the password we chose during the creation process;</li>
<li>click on the "Open" button.</li>
</ul>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_080.png" alt="zuluprovide" width="600" height="317" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_080-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_080-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_080-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_080-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_080-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_080-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>At this point, we can access the container with our file explorer.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_081.png" alt="zuludolphin" width="750" height="571" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_081-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_081-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_081-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_081-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_081-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_081-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>We are nor ready to copy our mnemonic seed to the container. Since we are working in a live environment, we do not need to delete it.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_082.png" alt="mnemonic in container" width="750" height="430" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_082-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_082-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_082-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_082-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_082-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_082-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>At this point we can unmount our volume, by right-clicking on it in the ZuluCrypt GUI and selecting the "Unmount" option.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/Selection_083.png" alt="zuluunmount" width="750" height="436" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_083-xs.png 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_083-sm.png 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_083-md.png 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_083-lg.png 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_083-xl.png 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/44/responsive/Selection_083-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<h3>How to store our container</h3>
<p>We do not have to forget that we are working in a live environment and, if we shut down the system, our cointainer will be irremediably lost. So, before shutting down our system, we should save it somewhere. We could put it on an encrypted drive or into another encrypted container we have previously created using <a href="https://anubitux.org/create-encrypted-volumes-with-veracrypt/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VeraCrypt</a> or some other <a href="https://anubitux.org/anubitux-and-encrypted-storages/">similar solution</a>.</p>
<p>Now, when we are sure our hidden container is in a safe place, we can shut down our system without connecting it to the Internet and also restarting it if we need to perform other operations.</p>
<h3>Final thoughts</h3>
<p>There could be infinite other solutions to safely store our mnemonic seed. This has not to be considered the best way to do this but only a suggestion on how to do that in a creative and secure way.</p>
<p>We also need to remember that more is the security we add to our information, the more it could be difficult for us to recover it if we lose or forget the right credentials.</p>
<p>It is also recommended to have more copies of the file hiding the container since the device we are storing it on could get broken or lost at any time and for many different unpredictable reasons.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>From wax tablets to elliptical curves. A Brief History of Cryptography (Part One)</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/from-wax-tablets-to-elliptical-curves-a-brief-history-of-cryptography-part-one/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/from-wax-tablets-to-elliptical-curves-a-brief-history-of-cryptography-part-one/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/main.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="opsec"/>
            <category term="encryption"/>
            <category term="cryptography"/>
            <category term="cryptocurrency"/>
            <category term="crypto"/>

        <updated>2023-01-09T14:40:37+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/main.jpg" alt="" />
                    With this article we inaugurate the section "what about cryptos?" in which we will insert a few articles regarding the fundamentals of cryptocurrencies. Specifically, let's kick off with this 3-article series, taken entirely from the respective articles published on our Osintops.com project here, with which&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/main.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>With this article we inaugurate the section "what about cryptos?" in which we will insert a few articles regarding the fundamentals of cryptocurrencies.</p>
<p>Specifically, let's kick off with this 3-article series, taken entirely from the respective articles published on our Osintops.com project <a href="https://osintops.com/dalle-tavolette-di-cera-alle-curve-ellittiche-prima-parte/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>, with which we will take a short journey (certainly not exhaustive) in the history of cryptography from its origins, as they have come down to us through the writings of some historians, passing through the algorithms and methods that have marked a turning point, up to mentioning the elliptical cryptography, from which the Bitcoin protocol drew.</p>
<p>In apologizing to those who have spent countless hours studying these cryptographic algorithms and to the more skilled readers, I want to clarify that this is not intended to be a technical article or intended for experts in the subject. Rather, it is the first step of a journey that will serve to become familiar with some very popular terms and concepts.<br>Perhaps it will help us better understand what is under the hood of some procedures that we now take for granted, which we carry out with mechanical gestures, such as electronic signatures.</p>
<p>The book “ <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Code-Book-Science-Secrecy-Cryptography/dp/0385495323/ref=sr_1_2?crid=3FELF5VGDR3VG&amp;keywords=simon+singh&amp;qid=1669827671&amp;sprefix=simon+sing%2Caps%2C195&amp;sr=8-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Code Book: The Science of Secrecy from Ancient Egypt to Quantum Cryptography</a>" by Simon Singh was a great source of inspiration for me and a stimulus to delve into these topics. I think it is an exciting starting point for all those who approach this subject, even if only out of pure curiosity.</p>
<p>Men have always had the need to be able to send communications that were understandable only to the people for whom they were intended. At the same time other men tried to understand its meaning, thus starting the perennial competition between inventors and code solvers.</p>
<p>This need for confidentiality in communications reached such a level of importance that it was soon seen fit to create an appropriate branch of science, cryptography. On the other hand, cryptanalysis is the discipline that studies the methods for restoring the plain text, starting from the encrypted message without knowing the key.</p>
<h3>The first methods to hide a message</h3>
<p>In the Bible we can observe one of the oldest ancient cryptographic methods. In the book of Jeremiah, in fact, some words have been replaced by others (Babel has been transcribed with the word Sheshakh) using a monoalphabetic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Substitution_cipher" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">substitution cipher</a> called Atbash, in which the first letter of the alphabet is replaced by the last, the second by penultimate and so on, until obtaining an inverted alphabet.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47//1.jpg" alt="" width="330" height="538" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47//responsive/1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47//responsive/1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47//responsive/1-md.jpg 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47//responsive/1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47//responsive/1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47//responsive/1-2xl.jpg 1600w">
<figcaption >First example of steganography according to Herodotus' account, 480 BC</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Among the first authors to narrate examples of cryptography we find the historian Herodotus who, in his Histories dedicated to the wars between the Greeks and the Persians in the fifth century BC, states that it was the secret writing that saved Greece from Xerxes, king of the Persians. He tells of an episode in which, to get a message to Leonidas (king of the Greeks) who then decreed the victory of the Greeks over the Persians, the wax was scraped off a writing tablet and the message was engraved on the underlying wood, covering the tablet again with wax. This trick turns out to be one of the first examples of steganography known to date, a technique considered the ancestor of cryptography since, as the etymology of the word itself suggests, it serves to cover and not to encode a message (from the Greek steganós = covered and gráphein = to write).</p>
<p>Methods to hide messages were also studied and adopted in the Asian continent. In particular, in China, the message to be transmitted was painted on strips of silk. These strips, rolled up, were covered in wax and ingested by the messenger. Once at its destination, the message was recovered with techniques that I prefer not to imagine. They were probably the first "ovulators", at present famous for transporting another type of goods :-).</p>
<p>Over the following centuries, almost all civilizations have adopted methods and stratagems to conceal and make it difficult to decipher the messages deemed important. This system, albeit very ingenious, had the major limitation of leaving the message unencrypted, even if covered up.</p>
<p>An important step forward in this virtual battlefield was the development of cryptography (from the Greek kryptós = hidden), going from hiding the message by concealing it in the most disparate ways so as not to let it be found by anyone who was not the recipient, to hiding the meaning of the message, encrypting it with alterations agreed with the recipient, who only had to reverse the procedure, obtaining the original text.<br>Encryption can be done in two ways: by substitution and by transposition.</p>
<p>In substitution cryptography it is necessary to swap each letter of the alphabet with another, shifting the alphabet by a constant number of positions. With this method the position of the letters within the alphabet always remains the standard one, both in the original message and in the one used for encryption.</p>
<p>One of the first and most famous examples of this encryption method was the so-called Caesar Cipher, the use of which by Julius Caesar himself was narrated in his De bello gallico.</p>
<p>Transposition encryption, on the other hand, causes the letters of the original message to swap places with each other, effectively forming an anagram. To increase the security of this method, it should be used on long enough messages.</p>
<p>Ultimately, if in substitution encryption each character of the original message is simply shifted by a predetermined number of positions, always retaining its original place within the alphabet, in transposition encryption each letter represents itself, but is placed in a different position, mixing the letters and thus forming a large anagram of the sentence.</p>
<p>Over the centuries it has been seen that these methods were rather weak, also because of the birth of cryptanalysis, a science born of Arab civilization in the Middle Ages which set itself the goal of interpreting messages without knowing the relative keys.</p>
<p>One of the pioneers of what would later become a real scientific discipline was a scientist of Arab origins (not surprisingly!), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Kindi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abū Yūsuf Yaʿqūb ibn Isḥāq al-Kindī</a>, known as Al-Kindi. In addition to being a philosopher and having had the merit of importing the thoughts of the great Greek philosophers into the Arab world, he was the first to devise a method which made it possible to decipher a text by analyzing the frequencies of the letters used, laying the foundations for creating frequency analysis cryptanalysis.</p>
<p>All this has led, over time, to the search for increasingly complex methods in order to make the job of deciphering messages more difficult.</p>
<p>The history of cryptography has seen artistic personalities of the caliber of Leon Battista Alberti at its service, who used two cipher alphabets for the first time, or Blaise de Vigenère who, with his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vigen%C3%A8re_cipher" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vigenère Table</a>, adopted 26 cipher alphabets, laying the foundations for modern encryption systems.</p>
<p>With the invention of the radio, by Guglielmo Marconi in 1894, people began to think about remote communication and, of course, to apply message encryption techniques, especially in the military sphere. Given the simplicity and speed of communication of texts via radio waves, efforts to create ever more complex encryption methods increased and parallel attempts at decryption intensified.</p>
<p>Since it was above all during the world wars that these coded messages assumed extreme importance, a battle within a battle was created: if on the one hand traditional weapons were used to gain positions in the enemy camp, on the other front the weapons were represented by numbers, spaces and letters. One of the first radio encryption methods was invented by the Germans and was called <a href="https://crypto.interactive-maths.com/adfgvx-cipher.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ADFGVX</a>.</p>
<p>Subsequently, in an attempt to create an inviolable system, an American engineer and mathematician, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claude_Shannon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude Shannon</a>, adapted Vigenère 's system, however introducing the concept of a random key, inserted into a sheet filled with random letters which, with hundreds of other similar sheets, formed a block, an identical copy of which would be used by both the sender and the recipient: hence the name of single- use block cipher (= one-time pad cipher), considered the Holy Grail of cryptography since it was many years an absolutely safe method.</p>
<h3>The cipher machines</h3>
<figure ><figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/2.jpg" alt="" width="250" height="273" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/2-md.jpg 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figcaption >CaptioEnigma cipher machinen</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>At the end of this brief historical review of cryptographic methods, certainly not exhaustive, we cannot fail to mention the Enigma cipher machine, conceived by the German inventor Scherbius and adopted by the military forces of the Reich. This ingenious device, in the shape of a typewriter, made it possible to type the message (in the clear text) on the keys and to see the encrypted text appear on a viewer which lit up the letters corresponding to the already encrypted message. The main invention of this machine was located inside, where 2 or 3 rotating exchangers were placed which, with each pressure of the keys, rotated by one position thus providing a very high possibility of combinations.</p>
<p>We could imagine a hypothetical operator sitting in front of this cipher machine, pressing the keys on the letters of the keyboard of the Enigma machine reporting the message to be sent (in clear text). After pressing the key, the electrical impulse crossed the rotors following a path defined by the position of the same and returned back thanks to a reflector, always crossing the rotors. Following this path, the impulse illuminated the light of the letter resulting from the encryption on a special viewer, which the operator then proceeded to transcribe. With each further press of the keys the rotors rotated one position at a time (there were 26 for each rotor, at the end of the revolution of the first rotor, the second would move one position and so on) allowing so the operator to use a polyalphabetic substitution cipher. Since this system could also be used to decrypt messages received with the same system, it was essential to position the rotors of the sending and receiving machines in the same position. This was made possible by means of a register of the daily positions of the rotors distributed to all the units used, through which each operator could have adjusted their rotors based on what was reported in the same, it was a sort of daily calendar of the positions to be applied.</p>
<p>It was thanks to the efforts of Polish analysts in the first place and then a brilliant team of English cryptanalysts that the German messages were deciphered.</p>
<p>In the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GCHQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Government School of Codes and Digits</a>, established in Bletchley Park in England, the brightest minds of England were recruited to solve the puzzle called Enigma.</p>
<figure ><figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/3.jpg" alt="" width="490" height="740" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/3-xs.jpg 300w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/3-sm.jpg 480w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/3-md.jpg 768w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/3-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/3-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://anubitux.org/media/posts/47/responsive/3-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figcaption >Turing bomb</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The intuition of the young mathematician Alan Turing was decisive in this dispute.</p>
<p>Based on his studies concerning a programmable universal logic machine, called Turing machine, he had a calculator built, called Bomb, which was able to quickly determine the initial positions of the rotors of the Enigma machine, thus allowing the decipherment of the entire message. On the subject, in addition to countless books, ranging from historical accounts to science fiction, we like to point out the beautiful film <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Imitation_Game" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Imitation Game</a>.</p>
<p>A few years later, in Bletchley Park, in order to decipher the messages of the German cipher device Lorenz SZ40/42, which represented the evolution of the Enigma machine, the mathematician <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Max_Newman#cite_note-frs-3," target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Newman</a>, always starting from Turing's studies on the universal machine, built the Colossus calculator, which was not only decisive in decrypting thousands of messages considered indecipherable at the time, but represents the first example of a programmable computer in the history of information technology, laying the foundations for the creation of modern electronic computers.</p>
<p>These exceptional facts have remained unknown for many years, due to the secrecy imposed by the British government, which forced all the protagonists to absolute secrecy and ordered the destruction of the electronic calculators built.</p>
<h5 class="align-center"><em><a href="https://anubitux.org/from-wax-tablets-to-elliptical-curves-a-brief-history-of-cryptography-part-two/">Part two</a></em></h5>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>HO HO HO! It&#x27;s Christmas time for Anu₿itux!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu₿itux</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anubitux.org/ho-ho-ho-its-christmas-time-for-anubitux/"/>
        <id>https://anubitux.org/ho-ho-ho-its-christmas-time-for-anubitux/</id>
        <media:content url="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/43/AnubituxWallpaperChristmas.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="ubuntu"/>
            <category term="project"/>
            <category term="live"/>
            <category term="linux for xmr"/>
            <category term="linux for cryptocurrencies"/>
            <category term="linux for crypto"/>
            <category term="linux for bitcoin"/>
            <category term="linux"/>
            <category term="links"/>
            <category term="kubuntu"/>
            <category term="downloads"/>
            <category term="download"/>
            <category term="distro"/>
            <category term="cryptocurrency"/>
            <category term="crypto"/>
            <category term="anubitux"/>

        <updated>2022-12-01T07:22:00+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/43/AnubituxWallpaperChristmas.png" alt="" />
                    Check out this new customized Anu₿itux! A very cool Christmas theme with some gifts! New tools and updates in it! The distro has received Kubuntu's updates. Also Tor Browser and many wallet softwares have been updated. The BitWarden password manager has been added, so you&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://anubitux.org/media/posts/43/AnubituxWallpaperChristmas.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Check out this new customized Anu₿itux! A very cool Christmas theme with some gifts! New tools and updates in it!</p>
<p>The distro has received Kubuntu's updates. Also Tor Browser and many wallet softwares have been updated.</p>
<p>The BitWarden password manager has been added, so you can manage more passwords in your working environment.</p>
<p>And, last but not least, a new tool by the <a href="https://anubitux.org/meet-the-anubitux-project/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Anu₿itux team</a>! Try to type password in your terminal and a new secure password will be <a href="https://github.com/ASeriousMister/passgen.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">generated</a> every time you'll need it. Do not forget to store it somewhere if you used it. Anu₿itux is not going to store anything, as always. Your security lies only on you!</p>
<p><a href="https://anubitux.org/download-anubitux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Grab</a> your Christmas version of Anu₿itux! It will be available only for a limited time!</p>
<p class="msg msg--success align-center"><strong>Merry Christmas from the Anu₿itux team!!!</strong></p>
<p align="center"><div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="480" height="352" src="https://giphy.com/embed/11BEQyXROgnLTG" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<h5>Don't trust...verify!</h5>
<p><code>-----BEGIN PGP SIGNED MESSAGE-----</code><br><code>Hash: SHA512</code><br><br><code>AnuBitux_2022_1_8_christmas.iso</code><br><code>MD5: 62ef19470079359852e7a73292785960</code><br><code>Sha256: 14974507afd7c0c6656111ccc85c84f0b3460d7e18be1246b427c2c1c2a92506</code><br><code>-----BEGIN PGP SIGNATURE-----</code><br><br><code>iQGzBAEBCgAdFiEEefEIBKtGU1BmKiujyYDLEerEolUFAmOCLVkACgkQyYDLEerE</code><br><code>olWlNgwApKkJm1Z0VhGrIhh4r5DeYa0rqAC+6eheG/uY+RMofRNByWolK4Ah2Zss</code><br><code>S/1E+S9mt4DdY6llRhWe1KdPc3vJlivnor8gxYQ935Vz5cMLWI90/TE7VQ+QcnIt</code><br><code>ZnLLNWHzG8GrC8KFsC+Yxt6KbYBQBo2th08P11lUFVAhQNkA00Eihsri7ET8Y3bZ</code><br><code>WQvqX7PE2RW2YcUqGGWeld+goJYs2Ug28wXjCecZQ53yt/KrscmYfM6H+LhWDnKs</code><br><code>xU1OZciJTlYkJvLnnAPKO5Vct/L/1xnzFoq2lunzPonSyB+td+QZIlwHKM/yW6c1</code><br><code>s2S5K6sfqN8fEWEeWrHqZDbkacyaEToyVk0NuUCDnr8QkALwQEo3IvHAzvo5GqB6</code><br><code>HihgyE/CRD1NJhvLBqwCO8hYvevDay0DReKuQ1et3G5msWmmgZg65ioTJn06BQbK</code><br><code>5RzWOZ+f8996RbGNjfP+gAkjeVOp2gxvZAlZONgB50/63K2xlb3aCzVzWSJoTI4K</code><br><code>JjpiLAng</code><br><code>=8Xl3</code><br><code>-----END PGP SIGNATURE-----</code></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
